Guide to the Paul Dougherty Papers on Save St. Brigid's AIA.097
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Paul Dougherty Papers on Save St. Brigid's
1952-2025
2003-2013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dougherty, Paul
AIA.097
1.92 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 oversize flat box
3 MiniDV
2.90 Gigabytes in 173 computer files
Paul Dougherty is a video editor who lives in the East Village. He was also a member of the Save St. Brigid's Committee with a strong family connection to the Church and School. St. Brigid's Roman Catholic Church (also known as the Famine Church) is located in New York City's East Village. The Church building was constructed in 1848 on what was once a dry dock district on the eastern side of Manhattan. Construction was undertaken by Irish shipbuilders who used shipbuilding techniques to design the building, and the church parish was originally primarily attended by Irish immigrants, later Irish Americans, and later still became a central place of worship for the largely Latine communities living in the Alphabet City neighborhood. The Church, led by the efforts of Father George Kuhn, often supported unhoused persons and activists. Upon demolition of St. Brigid's School, it became clear that the structure of the school had been shoring up the Church, after which cracks developed in the walls. The community rallied to save the church, including creating a committee called Save St. Brigid's. The Church was closed for roughly five years. In 2013, the newly renovated building was consecrated and dedicated. The Paul Dougherty Papers on Save St. Brigid's (dated 1952-2025, bulk 2003-2013) consists of materials created and collected by Dougherty documenting the efforts of the Save St. Brigid's Committee to save and repair St. Brigid's Roman Catholic Church in New York City. Materials include photographs, media coverage of the effort to save the church, meeting agendas, emails and other correspondence, contracting proposals, petitions for landmark status, speeches given at rallies and demonstrations, and flyers for benefits and other gatherings to draw attention to the cause and to fundraise for it.
Scope and Contents
The Paul Dougherty Papers on Save St. Brigid's (dated 1952-2025, bulk 2003-2013) consists of materials created and collected by Dougherty documenting the efforts of the Save St. Brigid's Committee to save, repair, and preserve St. Brigid's Roman Catholic Church in New York City. Materials include photographs, media coverage of the effort to save the church, meeting agendas, emails and other correspondence, contracting proposals, petitions for landmark status, speeches given at rallies and demonstrations, and flyers for benefits and other gatherings to draw attention to the cause and to fundraise for it.
Arrangement
Physical materials have not been arranged by an archivist, and are in the order in which they were received from the donor. Born-digital materials have been grouped by topic, maintaining much of the creator's original order.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Paul Dougherty in December 2025; the accession number associated with this gift is 2025.105.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Historical Note
St. Brigid's Roman Catholic Church (also known as the Famine Church) is located in New York City's East Village. The Church building was constructed in 1848 on what was once a dry dock district on the eastern side of Manhattan. Construction was undertaken by Irish shipbuilders who used shipbuilding techniques to design the building, and the church parish was originally primarily attended by Irish immigrants, later Irish Americans, and later still became a central place of worship for the largely Latine communities living in the Alphabet City neighborhood. The Church, led by the efforts of Father George Kuhn, often supported unhoused persons and activists. Upon demolition of St. Brigid's School, it became clear that the structure of the school had been shoring up the Church, after which cracks developed in the walls. The community rallied to save the church, including creating a committee called Save St. Brigid's. The Church was closed for roughly five years. In 2013, the newly renovated building was consecrated and dedicated.
Biographical Note
Paul Dougherty is a video editor who lives in the East Village. He is also a member of the Save St. Brigid's Committee with a strong family connection to the Church and School.
Appraisal
Digital surrogates of materials present in the physical collection, including scans of newspapers, were appraised out of the collection.
East Village (New York, N.Y.); Ireland -- History -- Famine, 1845-1852; Shipbuilding industry -- Employees; Ireland -- Emigration and immigration.; Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Church buildings.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Church architecture -- Conservation and restoration.; Dougherty, Paul; St. Brigid's Church (New York, N.Y.)
- Pre-Benefit, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Restoration, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- History, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- History, Clippings, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- History, Programs, 2008, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Notes, 2003-2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Clippings, 2006-2013 (Box 1, Folder 8, Box 2, Folder 1-6)
- Clippings, Research, 2005-2021 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bards for St. Brigid's, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "The History of St. Brigid's Parish in the City of New York Under the Administration of the Rev. Patrick F. McSweeny" (Dissertation by Rev. Patrick D. O'Flaherty), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Handbills, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Notes, Correspondence, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Benefit at Connolly's, 2006 June 15; cuid45192
  - Tape 1, cuid45193 (Box Shared Tamiment 202, Minidv cuid45193)
  - Tape 2, cuid45194 (Box Shared Tamiment 202, Minidv cuid45194)
- Press Conference, circa 2006-2013; cuid45195 (Box Shared Tamiment 202, Minidv cuid45195)
- Victory Press Conference, 2008 May 21; TW_AIA_097_ER_1
- Dougherty Family History, 2025; TW_AIA_097_ER_2
- Email Correspondence, 2006-2008; TW_AIA_097_ER_3
- History of St. Brigid's, 2025; TW_AIA_097_ER_4
- Saved and Renovated Photographs and Video Recording, 2023-2025; TW_AIA_097_ER_5
- Press Coverage, 2005-2008; TW_AIA_097_ER_6
- Photographs -- General, circa 2005-2008; TW_AIA_097_ER_7
- Connolly's Bards for St. Brigid's Benefit, 2006; TW_AIA_097_ER_8
- Photographs -- After Closure, 2001-2007; TW_AIA_097_ER_9
- Architectural Evaluation by John J. Flynn, 2003; TW_AIA_097_ER_10
- Letter from Cardinal Egan, 2006; TW_AIA_097_ER_11
- Benefit and Campaign Documentation, circa 2005-2008; TW_AIA_097_ER_12
- "Old St. Brigid's" -- Audio and Video Recordings, undated; TW_AIA_097_ER_13
- "Save St. Brigid's" Documentary, circa 2005-2008; TW_AIA_097_ER_14